Well, speaking of the northern area, the population that left Barra Funda
Pues bien, incluso en la Zona Norte esta población que sale de la Barra fundada,
and the downtown areas started to build other spaces, other territories:
que deja una parte del centro también,
Casa Verde, Peruche, and Brasilândia. They're also territories of blacks.
casa verde, Peruche, que son también territorios negros, la Brasilândia es un territorio negro.
Another share of that population went to the southern region,
Tenemos también otro frente que va hacia la Zona Sur:
to the Jabaquara neighbourhood, another important territory of blacks.
Jabaquara es un territorio negro importante,
Historically, the Jabaquara quilombo was based on it...
que históricamente ha albergado el quilombo del Jabaquara ...
And... well, what about it? It had a very, very complicated history.
Bueno, el quilombo del Jabaquara es una historia muy complicada, ¿verdad?
It's hard to recognize the history of a place, isn't it?
Es difícil reconocer la historia del lugar, ¿no?
There's a political purpose in the construction of history.
La construcción de la historia e política también, ¿no?
Where today is Sítio da Ressaca House was once the Jabaquara quilombo.
Donde hoy es la casa del "Sítio da Ressaca", era antes el quilombo del Jabaquara.
You may find it odd, "a quilombo in the middle of the city?"
"Pero un quilombo en la ciudad de Sao Paulo?"
The Saracura quilombo was located here too!
Había el quilombo de la Saracura!
It was the first urban quilombo of Sao Paulo.
Ha sido el primer quilombo urbano de São Paulo.